Hi everyone. Hope you're well.
And uh next up what I'd like to do is
I'd like to build out make more.
Like micrograd before it, make more is a
repository that I have on my GitHub
webpage. Uh you can look at it. Uh but
just like with micrograd, I'm going to
build it out step-by-step and I'm going
to spell everything out. So, we're going
to build it out slowly and together.
Now, what is make more?
Make more, uh as the name suggests, uh
makes more of things that you give it.
So, here's an example. names.txt is an
example data set to make more.
And when you look at names.txt, you'll
find that it's a very large data set of
names.
So,
here's lots of different types of names.
In fact, I believe there are 32,000
names that I've sort of found randomly
on a government website.
And if you train make more on this data
set, it will learn to make more of
things like this. Um and in particular
in this case, that will mean more things
that sound name-like, but are actually
unique names. And maybe if you have a
baby and you're trying to assign name,
maybe you're looking for a cool new
sounding unique name, make more might
help you.
So, here are some example generations
from the neural network once we train it
on our data set.
So, here's some example unique names
that it will generate. Dontal,
uh Irot,
uh Zendy,
and so on.
And so, all these sort of sound
name-like, uh but they're not, of
course, names.
So, under the hood, make more is a
character-level language model. So, what
that means is that it is treating every
single line here as an example.
And within each example, it's treating
them all as sequences of individual
characters. So, r e e s e is this
example, and that's the sequence of
characters, and that's the level on
which we are building out make more.
And what it means to to a
character-level language model then is
that it's just sort of modeling those
sequences of characters and it knows how
to predict the next character in the
sequence.
Now, we're actually going to implement a
large number of character level language
models in terms of the neural networks
that are involved in predicting the next
character in a sequence. So, very simple
bigram and bag of word models,
multi-layer perceptrons, recurrent
neural networks, all the way to modern
transformers. In fact, the transformer
that we will build will be basically the
equivalent transformer to GPT-2 if you
have heard of GPT. Uh so, that's kind of
a big deal. It's a modern network and by
the end of this series you will actually
understand how that works
um on the level of characters.
Now, to give you a sense of the
extensions here, uh after characters we
will probably spend some time on the
word level so that we can generate
documents of words, not just little, you
know, segments of characters.
Uh but we can generate entire large,
much larger documents.
And then we're probably going to go into
images and image text uh networks such
as DALL-E, Stable Diffusion, and so on.
But for now we have to start
uh here, character level language
modeling. Let's go.
So, like before we are starting with a
completely blank Jupyter notebook page.
The first thing is I would like to
basically load up the data set
names.txt.
So, we're going to open up names.txt for
reading.
And we're going to read in everything
into a massive string.
And then, because it's a massive string,
we'd only like the individual words and
put them in a list.
So, let's call splitlines on that string
to get all of our words as a Python list
of strings.
So, basically we can look at for example
the first 10 words
and we have that it's a list of Emma,
Olivia, Ava, and so on.
And if we look at
the top of the page here, that is indeed
what we see.
Um
So, that's good.
This list actually makes me feel that
this is probably sorted by frequency.
But okay, so these are the words. Now,
we'd like to actually like learn a
little bit more about this data set.
Let's look at the total number of words.
We expect this to be roughly 32,000.
And then what is the for example
shortest word?
So min of
len of each word for W in words. So the
shortest word will be length two.
And max of len W for W in words. So the
longest word will be
15 characters.
So let's now think through our very
first language model.
As I mentioned, a character-level
language model is predicting the next
character in a sequence given already
some concrete sequence of characters
before it.
Now, what we have to realize here is
that every single word here, like
Isabella,
is actually quite a few examples packed
in to that single word.
Because what is a an existence of a word
like Isabella in the data set telling us
really? It's saying that
the character I is a very likely
character to come first in the sequence
of a name.
The character S is likely to come
after I.
The character A is likely to come after
IS.
The character B is very likely to come
after ISA. And so on all the way to A
following Isabella.
And then there's one more example
actually packed in here.
And that is that
after there's Isabella,
the word is very likely to end.
So that's one more sort of explicit
piece of information that we have here.
That we have to be careful with.
And so there's a lot packed into a
single individual word in terms of the
statistical structure of what's likely
to follow in these character sequences.
And then of course we don't have just an
individual word. We actually have 32,000
of these. And so there's a lot of
structure here to model.
Now, in the beginning what I'd like to
start with is I would like to start with
building a bigram language model.
Now, in a bigram language model, we're
always working with just two characters
at a time.
So, we're only looking at one character
that we are given, and we're trying to
predict the next character in the
sequence.
So, um what characters are likely to
follow R? What characters are likely to
follow A? And so on. And we're just
modeling that kind of a little local
structure.
And we're forgetting the fact that we
may have a lot more information. We're
always just looking at the previous
character to predict the next one. So,
it's a very simple and weak language
model, but I think it's a great place to
start.
So, now let's begin by looking at these
bigrams in our data set and what they
look like. And these bigrams, again, are
just two characters in a row.
So, for W words,
each W here is an individual word
string.
We want to iterate uh for
in We want to iterate this word
with consecutive characters. So, two
characters at a time, sliding it through
the word. Now, a interesting, nice way,
cute way to do this in Python, by the
way, is doing something like this. For
character one, character two in zip off
W and W at one.
one colon
print
character one, character two
And let's not do all the words. Let's
just do the first three words. And I'm
going to show you in a second how this
works.
But for now, basically, as an example,
let's just do the very first word alone,
Emma.
You see how we have a Emma, and this
will just print EM, MM, MA.
And the reason this works is because W
is the string Emma, W at one colon is
the string MMA,
and zip takes two iterators, and it
pairs them up, and then creates an
iterator over the tuples of their
consecutive entries.
And if any one of these lists is shorter
than the other, then it will just uh
halt and return.
So basically, uh that's why we return E
M M M M M M A,
but then because this iterator, the
second one here, runs out of elements,
zip just ends, and that's why we only
get these tuples. So, pretty cute.
So, these are the consecutive elements
in the first word.
Now, we have to be careful because we
actually have more information here than
just these three examples. As I
mentioned, we know that E is the is very
come first, and we know that A in this
case is coming last.
So, one way to do this is basically
we're going to create a special array
here of characters.
And
we're going to hallucinate a special
start token here.
I'm going to
call it like special start.
So, this is a list of one element plus
W
and then plus a special end character.
And the reason I'm wrapping the list of
W here is because W is a string in a
list of W will just have the individual
characters in the list.
And then doing this again now, but not
iterating over Ws but over the
characters,
will give us something like this.
So, E is likely So, this is a bigram of
the start character and E, and this is a
bigram of the A and the special end
character.
And now we can look at, for example,
what this looks like for
Olivia or Ava.
And indeed, we can actually
potentially do this for the entire data
set, but we won't print that. That's
going to be too much.
But these are the individual character
bigrams, and we can print them.
Now, in order to learn the statistics
about which characters are likely to
follow other characters, the simplest
way in the bigram language models is to
simply do it by counting.
So, we're basically just going to count
how often any one of these combinations
occurs in the training set.
In these words. So we're going to need
some kind of a dictionary that's going
to maintain some counts for every one of
these bigrams. So let's use a dictionary
B.
And this will map these bigrams. So
bigram is a tuple of character one
character two.
And then B at bigram
will be B.get of bigram
which is basically the same as B at
bigram.
But in the case that bigram is not in
the dictionary B, we would like to by
default return a zero.
Plus one.
So this will basically add up all the
bigrams and count how often they occur.
Let's get rid of printing.
Or rather
let's keep the printing and let's just
inspect what B is in this case.
And we see that many bigrams occur just
a single time. This one allegedly
occurred three times.
So A was an ending character three
times. And that's true for all of these
words.
All of Emma, Olivia, and Ava end with A.
Uh so that's why this occurred three
times.
Um
now let's do it for all the words.
Oops, I should not have printed.
I meant to erase that.
Let's kill this.
Let's just run.
And now B will have the statistics of
the entire data set.
So these are the counts across all the
words of the individual bigrams.
And we could for example look at some of
the most common ones and least common
ones.
Um this kind of grows in Python, but the
way to do this, the simplest way I like,
is we just use B.items.
B.items returns
the tuples of
key value. In this case the keys are the
character bigrams and the values are the
counts.
And so then what we want to do is we
want to do um
sorted of this.
Uh but by default sort is on the first
um
on the first item of a tuple, but we
want to sort by the values, which are
the second element of a tuple, that is
the key value.
So we want to use the key
equals lambda
uh that takes the key value
and returns the key value at the at one,
not at zero, but at one, which is the
count. So we want to sort by the count
of these elements.
And actually we want it to go backwards.
So here what we have is the bigram QNR
occurs only a single time.
Uh DZ occurred only a single time.
And when we sort this the other way
around,
we're going to see the most likely
bigrams. So we see that N was very often
an ending character
many, many times. And apparently N
almost always follows an A. And that's a
very likely combination as well.
Um
so
this is kind of the individual counts
that we achieve over the entire data
set.
Now it's actually going to be
significantly more convenient for us to
keep this information in a
two-dimensional array instead of a
Python dictionary.
So we're going to store this information
in a 2D array
and
the rows are going to be the first
character of the bigram and the columns
are going to be the second character.
And each entry in this two-dimensional
array will tell us how often that first
character follows the second character
in the data set.
So in particular, the array
representation that we're going to use
or the library is that of PyTorch.
And PyTorch is a deep learning neural
network framework, but part of it is
also this torch.tensor, uh which allows
us to create multi-dimensional arrays,
and manipulate them very efficiently.
So, let's import PyTorch, which you can
do by import torch.
And then we can create uh arrays.
So, let's create a array of zeros.
And we give it a um size of this array.
Let's create a 3x5 array as an example.
And
this is a 3x5 array of zeros.
And by default, you'll notice a data D
type, which is short for data type, is
float 32. So, these are single-precision
floating-point numbers.
Because we are going to represent
counts, let's actually use D type as
torch.int32.
So, these are uh
32-bit integers.
So, now you see that we have integer
data inside this tensor.
Now, tensors allow us to really um
manipulate all the individual entries
and do it very efficiently.
So, for example, if we want to change
this bit, we have to index into the
tensor. And in particular, here, this is
the first row, and the um because it's
zero-indexed. So, this is row index one,
and column index 0 1 2 3.
So, A at 1,3, we can set that to 1.
And then A will have a 1 over there.
We can of course also do things like
this. So, now A will be 2 over there.
Or 3.
And also, we can for example say A 0 0
is 5.
And then A will have a 5 over here.
So, that's how we can index into the
arrays. Now, of course, the array that
we are interested in is much much
bigger. So, for our purposes, we have 26
letters of the alphabet, and then we
have two special characters, S and E.
So, uh we want 26 + 2 or 28x28 array.
And let's call it the the N, because
it's going to represent sort of the
counts.
Let me erase this stuff.
So, that's the array that starts at
zeros, 28 by 28.
And now let's copy paste this
here.
But instead of having a dictionary be
which we're going to erase, we now have
an N.
Now, the problem here is that we have
these characters which are strings, but
we have to now
um basically index into a um array, and
we have to index using integers. So, we
need some kind of a lookup table from
characters to integers.
So, let's construct such a character
array.
And the way we're going to do this is
we're going to take all the words, which
is a list of strings.
We're going to concatenate all of it
into a massive string. So, this is just
simply the entire data set as a single
string.
We're going to pass this to the set
constructor, which takes this massive
string and throws out duplicates because
sets do not allow duplicates.
So, set of this will just be the set of
all the lowercase characters.
And there should be a total of 26 of
them.
And now we actually don't want a set, we
want a list.
But we don't want a list sorted in some
weird arbitrary way, we want it to be
sorted
from A to Z.
So, a sorted list.
So, those are our characters.
Now, what we want is this lookup table
as I mentioned. So, let's create a
special S2I, I will call it.
Um S is string or character, and this
will be an S2I mapping
for
IS in enumerate of these characters.
So, enumerate basically gives us this
iterator over the integer index and the
actual element of the list. And then we
are mapping the character to the
integer.
So, S2I
is a mapping from A to 0, B to 1, etc.
All the way from Z to 25.
And that's going to be useful here, but
we actually also have to specifically
set that S will be 26.
And S 2 I at E
will be 27, right? Because Z was 25.
So, those are the lookups. And now we
can come here and we can map both
character one and character two to their
integers.
So, this will be S 2 I at character one.
And IX2 will be S 2 I of character two.
And now we should be able to
do this line, but using our array. So, N
at IX1, IX2, this is the two-dimensional
array indexing I showed you before,
and honestly just plus equals one.
Because everything starts at zero.
So, this should work and give us a large
28 by 28 array
of all these counts. So, if we print N,
this is the array, but of course it
looks ugly. So, let's erase this ugly
mess and let's try to visualize it a bit
more nicer.
So, for that we're going to use a
library called Matplotlib.
So, Matplotlib allows us to create
figures. So, we can do things like
plt.imshow of the counter array.
So, this is the 28 by 28 array.
And this is a structure, but even this,
I would say, is still pretty ugly. So,
we're going to try to create a much
nicer visualization of it, and I wrote a
bunch of code for that.
Uh, the first thing we're going to need
is
we're going to need to invert this array
here, this um dictionary. So, S 2 I is a
mapping from S to I.
And in I 2 S, we're going to reverse
this dictionary. So, iterate over all
the items and just reverse that array.
So, I 2 S maps inversely from 0 to A, 1
to B, etc.
So, we'll need that.
And then here's the code that I came up
with to try to make this a little bit
nicer.
We create a figure.
We plot N.
And then we do and then we visualize a
bunch of things later. Let me just run
it so you get a sense of what all this
is.
Okay.
So, you see here that we have
the array spaced out. And every one of
these is basically like B follows G zero
times.
B follows H 41 times. Um so, A follows J
175 times.
And so, what you can see that I'm doing
here is first I show that entire array.
And then I iterate over all the
individual little cells here.
And I create a character string here.
Which is the inverse mapping I to S of
the integer I and the integer J. So,
that's These are the bigrams in a
character representation.
And then I plot just the bigram text.
And then I plot the number of times that
this bigram occurs.
Now, the reason that there's a dot item
here is because when you index into
these arrays, these are torch tensors.
You see that we still get a tensor back.
So, the type of this thing, you'd think
it would be just an integer 149, but
it's actually torch.tensor.
And so, if you do dot item, then it will
pop out that individual integer.
So, it'll just be 149.
So, that's what's happening there. And
these are just some options to make it
look nice.
So, what is the structure of this array?
Um
We have all these counts, and we see
that some of them occur often and some
of them do not occur often.
Now, if you scrutinize this carefully,
you will notice that we're not actually
being very clever.
That's because when you come over here,
you'll notice that for example, we have
an entire row of completely zeros. And
that's because the end character
is never possibly going to be the first
character of a bigram because we're
always placing these end tokens all at
the end of the bigram.
Similarly, we have entire columns of
zeros here because the S
character will never possibly be the
second element of a bigram because we
always start with S and we end with E
and we only have the words in between.
So, we have an entire column of zeros,
an entire row of zeros. And in this
little 2 by 2 matrix here as well, the
only one that can possibly happen is if
S directly follows E.
That can be non-zero if we have a word
that has no letters. So, in that case
there's no letters in the word, it's an
empty word and we just have S follows E.
But, the other ones are just not
possible.
And so, we're basically wasting space
and not only that, but the S and the E
are getting very crowded here.
I was using these brackets because
there's convention in natural language
processing to use these kinds of
brackets to denote special tokens. Uh
but, we're going to use something else.
So, let's fix all of this and make it
prettier.
We're not actually going to have two
special tokens, we're only going to have
one special token.
So, we're going to have n by n array of
27 by 27 instead.
Instead of having two, we will just have
one and I will call it a dot.
Okay?
Let me swing this over here.
Now, one more thing that I would like to
do is I would actually like to make this
special character have position zero and
I would like to offset all the other
letters off. I find that a little bit
more pleasing.
Um
so,
we need a plus one here so that the
first character, which is A, will start
at one.
So, S to I will now be A starts at one
and dot is zero.
And uh I to S, of course, we're not
changing this because I to S just
creates a reverse mapping and this will
work fine. So, one is A, two is B, zero
is dot.
So, we reverse that. Here,
we have
a dot and a dot.
This should work fine.
Make sure I start at zeros.
Count. And then here, we don't go up to
28, we go up to 27.
And this should just work.
Okay.
So, we see that dot dot never happened.
It's at zero because we don't have empty
words.
Then this row here now is just very
simply the
counts for all the first letters. So, G
J starts a word, H starts a word, I
starts a word, etc. And then these are
all the ending
characters.
And in between, we have the structure of
what characters follow each other.
So, this is the counts array of our
entire uh data set. So, this array
actually has all of the information
necessary for us to actually sample from
this bigram
character level language model.
And
roughly speaking, what we're going to do
is we're just going to start following
these probabilities and these counts,
and we're going to start sampling from
the from the model.
So, in the beginning, of course,
we start with the dot, the start token.
Dot. So, to sample the first character
of a name, we're looking at this row
here.
So, we see that we have the counts, and
those counts are telling are telling us
how often any one of these characters is
to start a word.
So, if we take this N,
and we grab the first row,
we can do that by using just indexing at
zero,
and then using this notation colon for
the rest of that row.
So, N zero colon
is indexing into the zeroth um row and
then it's grabbing all the columns.
And so this will give us a
one-dimensional array
of the first row. So 0 4 4 10.
You know it's 0 4 4 10 1 3 0 6 1 5 4 2
etc. It's just the first row.
The shape of this is 27. It's just a row
of 27.
And the other way that you can do this
also is you just you don't need to
actually give this
you just uh grab the zeroth row like
this. This is equivalent.
Now these are the counts.
And now what we'd like to do is we'd
like to basically um sample from this.
Since these are the raw counts, we
actually have to convert this to
probabilities.
So we create a probability vector.
So we'll take n of zero
and we'll actually convert this to float
first.
Okay, so these integers are converted to
float
a floating point numbers. And the reason
we're creating floats is because we're
about to normalize these counts.
So to create a probability distribution
here, we want to divide
we basically want to do p p p divide
p.sum.
And now we get a vector of smaller
numbers and these are now probabilities.
So of course because we divided by the
sum, the sum of p now is one.
So this is a nice proper probability
distribution. It sums to one and this is
giving us the probability for any single
character to be the first uh character
of a word.
So now we can try to sample from this
distribution. To sample from these
distributions, we're going to use
torch.multinomial which I've pulled up
here.
So torch.multinomial returns uh
um samples from the multinomial
probability distribution which is a
complicated way of saying you give me
probabilities and I will give you
integers which are sampled according to
the probability distribution.
So this is the signature of the method,
and to make everything deterministic,
we're going to use a generator object in
PyTorch.
Uh so, this makes everything
deterministic. So, you when you run this
on your computer, you're going to the
exact get the exact same results that
I'm getting here on my computer.
So, let me show you how this works.
Um
Here's the deterministic way of creating
a torch generator object,
seeding it with some number that we can
agree on.
So, that seeds a generator, gets gives
us an object G,
and then we can pass that G to a
function
that creates um
here random numbers. torch.rand creates
random numbers, three of them,
and it's using this generator object to
as a source of randomness.
Uh so, uh
without normalizing it,
I can just print.
Uh this is sort of like numbers between
zero and one that are random according
to this thing. And whenever I run it
again,
I'm always going to get the same result
because I keep using the same generator
object, which I'm seeding here.
And then if I divide
to normalize, I'm going to get a nice
probability distribution of just three
elements.
And then we can use torch.multinomial to
draw samples from it. So, this is what
that looks like.
torch.multinomial will take
the torch tensor
of probability distributions.
Then we can ask for a number of samples,
let's say 20.
replacement equals true means that when
we draw an element, uh we will uh we can
draw it, and then we can put it back
into the list of eligible indices to
draw again.
And we have to specify replacement as
true because by default, uh for for some
reason, it's false.
Um and I think,
you know, it's just something to be
careful with.
Uh and the generator is passed in here.
So, we are going to always get
deterministic results, the same results.
So, if I run these two,
we're going to get a bunch of samples
from this distribution.
Now, you'll notice here that the
probability for the first element in
this tensor is 60%.
So, in these 20 samples, we'd expect 60%
of them to be zero.
We'd expect 30% of them to be one.
And because the uh element index two
has only 10% probability, very few of
these samples should be two. And indeed,
we only have a small number of twos.
And we can sample as many as we would
like.
And the more we sample, the more uh
these numbers should um roughly have the
distribution here.
So, we should have lots of zeros, half
as many um
ones, and we should have um
three times as few
uh sorry, as few ones, and three times
as few uh
twos.
So, you see that we have very few twos,
we have some ones, and most of them are
zero. So, that's what torch.multinomial
is doing.
For us here,
we are interested in this row. We've
created this um
P here,
and now we can sample from it.
So, if we use the same seed,
and then we sample from this
distribution, let's just get one sample.
Then, we see that the sample is, say,
13.
Um so, this will be the index.
And let's You see how it's a tensor that
wraps 13. We again have to use that item
to pop out that integer.
And now, index would be just the number
13.
And of course, the um we can do we can
map the I2S of IX to figure out exactly
which character we're sampling here.
We're sampling M.
So, we're saying that the first
character is M in our generation.
And just looking at the row here,
M was drawn and you we can see that M
actually starts a large number of words.
M started 2,500 words out of 32,000
words. So, almost
a bit less than 10% of the words start
with M. So, this is actually fairly
likely character to draw.
Um
So, that would be the first character of
our word and now we can continue to
sample more characters because now we
know that M started
M is already sampled.
So, now to draw the next character, we
will come back here and we will look for
the row
that starts with M.
So, you see M
and we have a row here.
So, we see that M.
is
516, MA is this many, MB is this many,
etc. So, these are the counts for the
next row and that's the next character
that we are going to now generate. So, I
think we are ready to actually just
write out the loop because I think
you're starting to get a sense of how
this is going to go.
The um
We always begin at index zero because
that's the start token.
And then while true,
we're going to grab the row
corresponding to index
that we're currently on. So, that's P.
So, that's N array at IX.
Convert it to float is RP.
Then, we normalize this P to sum to one.
Accidentally ran the infinite loop.
We normalize P to sum to one.
Then we need this generator object
that we're going to initialize up here
and we're going to draw a single sample
from this distribution.
And then this is going to tell us what
index is going to be next.
If the index sampled is zero, then
that's now the end token.
So, we will break.
Otherwise, we are going to print
s2i of ix.
i2s of ix.
And uh that's pretty much it. We're just
uh this should work.
Okay, more.
So, that's the that's the name that
we've sampled. We started with M. The
next step was O, then R, and then dot.
And this dot we printed here as well.
So,
let's now do this a few times.
Um
So, let's actually create an
out list here.
And instead of printing, we're going to
append. So, out.append this character.
And then here, let's just print it at
the end. So, let's just join up all the
outs, and we're just going to print
more.
Okay? Now, we're always getting the same
result because of the generator.
So, if you want to do this a few times,
we can go for I in range
10. We can sample 10 names.
And we can just do that 10 times.
And these are the names that we're
getting out.
Let's do 20.
I'll be honest with you, this doesn't
look right.
So, I stared at it a few minutes to
convince myself that it actually is
right.
The reason these samples are so terrible
is that bigram language model
is actually like just like really
terrible.
We can generate a few more here.
And you can see that they're kind of
like their name-like a little bit, like
Keanu, O'Reilly, etc. Uh but they're
just like totally messed up. Um
And I mean, the reason that this is so
bad, like we're generating H as a name.
But you have to think through it from
the model's eyes. It doesn't know that
this H is the very first H. All it knows
is that H was previously, and now how
likely is H the last character? Well,
it's somewhat likely, and so it just
makes it last character. It doesn't know
that there were other things before it
or there were not other things before
it. And so, that's why it's generating
all these like sun- nonsense names.
Another way to do this is
to convince yourself that this is
actually doing something reasonable even
though it's so terrible is
these little piece here are 27, right?
Like 27.
So, how about if we did something like
this?
Instead of P having any structure
whatsoever,
how about if P was just a torch.ones of
27?
of 27.
By default, this is a float 32, so this
is fine. Divide 27.
So, what I'm doing here is this is the
uniform distribution, which will make
everything equally likely.
And we can sample from that. So, let's
see if that does any better.
Okay? So, it's This is what you have
from a model that is completely
untrained, where everything is equally
likely. So, it's obviously garbage. And
then if we have a trained model, which
is trained on just bigrams,
this is what we get. So, you can see
that it is more name-like. It is
actually working. It's just um
bigram is so terrible, and we have to do
better. Now, next I would like to fix an
inefficiency that we have going on here.
Because what we're doing here is we're
always fetching a row of N from the
counts matrix up ahead.
And we we're always doing the same
things. We're converting to float and
we're dividing and we're doing this
every single iteration of this loop and
we just keep re-normalizing these rows
over and over again and it's extremely
inefficient and wasteful.
So, what I'd like to do is I'd like to
actually prepare a matrix capital P that
will just have the probabilities in it.
So, in other words, it's going to be the
same as the capital N matrix here of
counts, but every single row will have
the row of probabilities uh that is
normalized to one indicating the
probability distribution for the next
character given the character before it.
Um as defined by which row we're in.
So, basically what we'd like to do is
we'd like to just do it up front here
and then we would like to just use that
row here.
Uh so, here we would like to just do P
equals P of IX instead.
Okay.
The other reason I want to do this is
not just for efficiency, but also I
would like us to practice uh these
N-dimensional tensors and I'd like us to
practice uh their manipulation and
especially something that's called
broadcasting that we'll go into in a
second.
We're actually going to have to become
very good at these tensor manipulations
because if we're going to build out all
the way to transformers, we're going to
be doing some pretty complicated um
array operations for efficiency and uh
we need to really understand that and be
very good at it.
So, intuitively what we want to do is we
first want to grab the floating point
copy of N.
And I'm mimicking the line here
basically.
And then we want to divide all the rows
so that they sum to one.
So, we'd like to do something like this.
P divide P.sum.
But, now we have to be careful
because P.sum actually
produces a sum
Sorry. P equals N.float.copy.
P.sum produces a um
sums up all of the counts of this entire
matrix N
and gives us a single number of just the
summation of everything. So, that's not
the way we want to defi- divide. We want
to simultaneously and in parallel divide
all the rows by their respective sums.
So, what we have to do now is we have to
go into documentation for torch.sum.
And we can scroll down here to a
definition that is relevant to us, which
is where we don't only provide an input
array that we want to sum, but we also
provide the dimension along which we
want to sum.
And in particular, we want to sum up uh
over rows, right?
Now, one more argument that I want you
to pay attention to here is the keepdim
is false.
If keepdim is true, then the output
tensor is of the same size as input,
except of course the dimension along
which you summed, which will become just
one.
But, if you pass in uh keepdim as false,
then this dimension is squeezed out. And
so, torch.sum not only does the sum and
collapses dimension to be of size one,
but in addition, it does what's called a
squeeze, where it squeeze out it
squeezes out that dimension.
So,
basically what we want here is we
instead want to do p.sum of sum axis.
And in particular, notice that p.shape
is 27 by 27.
So, when we sum up across axis zero,
then we would be taking the zeroth
dimension, and we would be summing
across it.
So, when keepdim is true,
then this thing will not only give us
the counts across um
along the columns,
but notice that basically the shape of
this is 1 by 27. We just get a row
vector.
And the reason we get a row vector here
again is because we pass in zero
dimension, so this zero dimension
becomes one, and we've done a sum,
and we get a row. And so, basically,
we've done the sum
this way,
vertically, and arrived at just a single
1 by 27
vector of counts.
What happens when you take out keepdim
is that we just get 27. So, it squeezes
out that dimension and we just get um
a one-dimensional vector of size 27.
Now, we don't actually want
1 by 27 row vector because that gives us
the counts or the sums across um
the uh columns.
We actually want to sum the other way
along dimension one.
And you'll see that the shape of this is
27 by one. So, it's a column vector.
It's a 27 by one
vector of counts.
Okay?
And that's because what's happened here
is that we're going horizontally and
this 27 by 27 matrix becomes a 27 by one
array.
Now, you'll notice by the way that um
the actual numbers
of these counts are identical.
And that's because this special array of
counts here comes from bigram
statistics. And actually, it just so
happens by chance or because of the way
this array is constructed that the sums
along the columns or along the rows,
horizontally or vertically, is
identical.
But actually, what we want to do in this
case is we want to sum across the uh
rows
horizontally. So, what we want here is
p.sum of one with keep dim true.
27 by one column vector.
And now, what we want to do is we want
to divide by that.
Now, we have to be careful here again.
Is it possible to take
what's a um p.shape you see here is 27
by 27. Is it possible to take a 27 by 27
array and divide it by what is a 27 by
one array?
Is that an operation that you can do?
And whether or not you can perform this
operation is determined by what's called
broadcasting rules. So, if you just
search broadcasting semantics in torch,
you'll notice that there's a special
definition for uh what's called
broadcasting that for whether or not
these two arrays can be combined in a
binary operation like division.
So the first condition is each tensor
has at least one dimension, which is the
case for us.
And then when iterating over the
dimension sizes starting at the trailing
dimension,
the dimension sizes must either be
equal, one of them is one, or one of
them does not exist.
Okay? So, let's do that. We need to
align the two arrays and their shapes,
which is very easy because both of these
shapes have two elements, so they're
aligned.
Then we iterate over from the from the
right and going to the left.
Each dimension must be either equal, one
of them is a one, or one of them does
not exist.
So in this case they're not equal, but
one of them is a one. So, this is fine.
And then this dimension, they're both
equal. So, this is fine.
So, all the dimensions are fine and
therefore the this operation is
broadcastable.
So that means that this operation is
allowed.
And what is it that these arrays do when
you divide 27 by 27 by 27 by one?
What it does is that it takes this
dimension one and it stretches it out.
It copies it
to match 27 here in this case.
So in our case, it takes this column
vector which is 27 by one
and it copies it 27 times
to make
these both be 27 by 27 internally. You
can think that way. And so it copies
those counts
and then it does an element-wise
division,
which is what we want because these
counts we want to divide by them on
every single one of these columns in
this matrix.
So this actually we expect will
normalize every single row.
And we can check that this is true by
taking the first row for example and
taking its sum. We expect this to be
one.
Because it's now normalized.
And then we expect this now, because if
we actually correctly normalize all the
rows, we expect to get the exact same
result here. So, let's run this.
It's the exact same result.
So, this is correct. So, now I would
like to scare you a little bit. Uh you
actually have to like I basically
encourage you very strongly to read
through broadcasting semantics.
And I encourage you to treat this with
respect. And it's not something to play
fast and loose with. It's something to
really respect, really understand, and
look up maybe some tutorials for
broadcasting and practice it, and be
careful with it because you can very
quickly run into bugs. Let me show you
what I mean.
You see how here we have p.sum of one,
keep dims is true.
The shape of this is 27 by one.
Let me take out this line just so we
have the n, and then we can see the
counts.
We can see that this is all the counts
across all the
rows.
And it's a 27 by one column vector,
right?
Now, suppose that I tried to do the
following,
but I erase keep dims is true here.
What does that do? If keep dims is not
true, it's false, then remember,
according to documentation, it gets rid
of this dimension one. It squeezes it
out. So, basically we just get all the
same counts, the same result, except the
shape of it is not 27 by one, it is just
27. The one disappears.
But all the counts are the same.
So, you think that this divide that
would would work.
First of all, can we even write this?
And will it Is it even Is it even
expected to run? Is it broadcastable?
Let's determine if this result is
broadcastable.
p.sum at one is shape
is 27.
This is 27 by 27. So, 27 by 27
broadcasting into 27.
So, now
rules of broadcasting, number one align
all the dimensions on the right done now
iteration over all the dimensions
starting from the right going to the
left
all the dimensions must either be equal
one of them must be one or one of them
does not exist so here they are all
equal here the dimension does not exist
so internally what broadcasting will do
is it will create a one here
and then
we see that one of them is a one and
this will get copied and this will run
this will broadcast
okay so you'd expect this to work
because we we are
this broadcasting this we can divide
this
now if I run this you'd expect it to
work but
it doesn't
you actually get garbage you get a wrong
result because this is actually a bug
this keep them equals true
makes it work
this is a bug in
both cases we are doing the correct
counts we are summing up across the rows
but keep them is saving us and making it
work so in this case
I'd like you to encourage you to
potentially like pause this video at
this point and try to think about why
this is buggy and why the keep them was
necessary here
okay
so the reason to do
for this is I'm trying to hint it here
when I was sort of giving you a bit of a
hint on how this works
this
27 vector
internally inside the broadcasting this
becomes a one by 27
and one by 27 is a row vector right and
now we are dividing 27 by 27 by one by
and torch will replicate this dimension
so basically
it will take
it will take this
row vector and it will copy it
vertically now
27 times so the 27 by 27 lines exactly,
and element twice divides.
And so, basically, what's happening here
is
um
we're actually normalizing the columns
instead of normalizing the rows.
So, you can check that what's happening
here is that P at zero, which is the
first row of P, dot sum is not one, it's
seven.
It is the first column, as an example,
that sums to one.
So,
to summarize, where does the issue come
from? The issue comes from the silent
adding of a dimension here because in
broadcasting rules, you align on the
right and go from right to left, and if
dimension doesn't exist, you create it.
So, that's where the problem happens. We
still did the counts correctly. We did
the counts across the rows, and we got
the the counts on the right here as a
column vector. But, because the keepdims
was true, this this uh this dimension
was discarded, and now we just have a
vector 27.
And because of broadcasting the way it
works, this vector of 27 suddenly
becomes a row vector.
And then this row vector gets replicated
vertically, and then every single point
we are dividing by the by the count
uh in the opposite direction.
So, uh
so, this thing just uh doesn't work. You
This needs to be keepdims equals true in
this case.
So, then
um then we have that P at zero is
normalized.
And conversely, the first column, you'd
expect to potentially not be normalized.
And this is what makes that work.
So, pretty subtle, and uh hopefully this
helps to scare you that you should have
a respect for broadcasting, be careful,
check your work,
uh and uh understand how it works under
the hood, and make sure that it's
broadcasting in the direction that you
like. Otherwise, you're going to
introduce very subtle bugs, very hard to
hard to find bugs, and uh just be
careful. One more note on efficiency, we
don't want to be doing this here because
uh this creates a completely new tensor
that we store into P. We prefer to use
in-place operations if possible.
Also, this would be an in-place
operation. It has the potential to be
faster. It doesn't create new memory
under the hood. And then let's erase
this. We don't need it.
And let's also
um just do fewer just so I'm not wasting
space.
Okay, so we're actually in a pretty good
spot now.
We trained a bigram language model, and
we trained it really just by counting
uh how frequently any pairing occurs and
then normalizing so that we get a nice
probability distribution.
So really these elements of this array P
are really the parameters of our bigram
language model giving us and summarizing
the statistics of these bigrams.
So we trained the model and then we know
how to sample from the model. We just
iteratively uh sample the next character
and uh feed it in each time and get the
next character.
Now what I'd like to do is I'd like to
somehow evaluate the quality of this
model.
We'd like to somehow summarize the
quality of this model into a single
number. How good is it at predicting uh
the training set?
And as an example, so in the training
set we can evaluate now the training
loss. And this training loss is telling
us about uh sort of the quality of this
model in a single number just like we
saw in micrograd.
So let's try to think through the
quality of the model and how we would
evaluate it.
Basically what we're going to do is
we're going to copy paste this code
that we previously used for counting.
Okay?
And let me just print the bigrams first.
We're going to use F-strings.
And I'm going to print character one
followed by character two. These are the
bigrams. And then I don't want to do it
for all the words. Let's just do the
first three words.
So here we have Emma, Olivia, and Ava
bigrams.
Now what we'd like to do is we'd like to
basically look at the probability that
the model assigns to every one of these
bigrams.
So, in other words, we can look at the
probability, which is summarized in the
matrix P,
of IX1 IX2.
And then we can print it here as
probability.
And because these probabilities are way
too large, let me percent uh
or colon point four F
to like truncate it a bit.
So, what do we have here, right? We're
looking at the probabilities that the
model assigns to every one of these
bigrams in the data set.
And so, we can see some of them are 4%,
3%, etc. Just to have a measuring stick
in our mind, by the way, um
with 27 possible characters or tokens,
and if everything was equally likely,
then you'd expect all these
probabilities to be
4% roughly.
So, anything above 4% means that we've
learned something useful from these
bigram statistics.
And you see that roughly some of these
are 4%, but some of them are as high as
40%,
35%, and so on. So, you see that the
model actually assigned a pretty high
probability to whatever's in the
training set. And so, that that's a good
thing.
Um basically, if you have a very good
model, you'd expect that these
probabilities should be near one,
because that means that uh your model is
correctly predicting what's going to
come next, especially in the training
set, where you where you trained your
model.
So, now we'd like to think about how can
we summarize these probabilities into a
single number that measures the quality
of this model.
Now, when you look at the literature
into maximum likelihood estimation and
statistical modeling and so on,
you'll see that what's typically used
here is something called the likelihood.
And the likelihood is the product of all
of these probabilities.
And so, the product of all of these
probabilities is the likelihood, and
it's really telling us about the
probability of the entire data set
assigned uh assigned by the model that
we've trained. And that is a measure of
quality.
So, the product of these should be as
high as possible
when you are training the model and when
you have a good model, your your product
of these probabilities should be very
high.
Um
Now, because the product of these
probabilities is an unwieldy thing to
work with, uh you can see that all of
them are between 0 and 1. So, your
product of these probabilities will be a
very tiny number.
Um so, for convenience, what people work
with usually is not the likelihood, but
they work with what's called the log
likelihood.
So,
the product of these is likelihood.
To get likelihood, we just have to take
the log of the probability.
And so, the log of the probability here,
I have a log of X from 0 to 1.
The log is a you see here monotonic
transformation of the probability,
where if you pass in 1, you get 0.
So, probability 1 gets you log
probability of 0.
And then, as you go lower and lower
probability, the log will grow more and
more negative until all the way to
negative infinity at 0.
So, here we have a log prob, which is
really just a torch. log of probability.
Let's print it out to get a sense of
what that looks like.
Log prob,
also point four if.
Okay.
So, as you can see, when we plug in
numbers that are very close, some of our
higher numbers, we get closer and closer
to 0.
And then, if we plug in very bad
probabilities, we get more and more
negative number. That's bad.
So,
and the reason we work with this is for
large extent convenience, right? Because
we have mathematically that if you have
some product A * B * C of all these
probabilities, right? Or the likelihood
is the product of all these
probabilities,
then the log
of these is just log of A plus log of B
plus log of C. If you remember your logs
from your
high school or undergrad and so on.
So we have that basically
the likelihood is the product of
probabilities, the log likelihood is
just the sum of the logs of the
individual probabilities.
So
log likelihood
starts at zero.
And then log likelihood here we can just
accumulate simply.
And in the end we can print this.
Print the log likelihood.
F strings.
Maybe you're familiar with this.
So log likelihood is -38.
Okay.
Now
we actually want um
So how high can log likelihood get? It
can go to zero. So when all the
probabilities are one, log likelihood
will be zero. And then when all the
probabilities are lower, this will grow
more and more negative.
Now we don't actually like this because
what we'd like is a loss function. And a
loss function has the semantics that low
is good. Because we're trying to
minimize the loss. So we actually need
to invert this. And that's what gives us
something called the negative log
likelihood.
Um
negative log likelihood is just negative
of the log likelihood.
These are F strings by the way if you'd
like to look this up.
Negative log likelihood equals
So negative log likelihood now is just
the negative of it.
And so the negative log likelihood is a
very nice loss function because um
the lowest it can get is zero. And the
higher it is, the worse off the
predictions are that you're making.
And then one more modification to this
that sometimes people do is that for
convenience uh they actually like to
normalize by they like to make it an
average instead of a sum.
And so here
let's just keep some counts as well.
So n plus equals one starts at zero. And
then here we can have sort of like a
normalized log likelihood.
Um
if we just normalize it by the count
then we will sort of get the average log
likelihood. So this would be usually our
loss function here.
This this we would this is what we would
use.
Uh so our loss function for the training
set assigned by the model is 2.4. That's
the quality of this model.
And the lower it is, the better off we
are. And the higher it is, the worse off
we are.
And the job of our, you know, training
is to find the parameters that minimize
the negative log likelihood loss.
And that would be like a high quality
model. Okay, so to summarize I actually
wrote it out here.
So our goal is to maximize likelihood
which is the product of all the
probabilities assigned by the model.
And we want to maximize this likelihood
with respect to the model parameters.
And in our case, the model parameters
here are defined in the table. These
numbers, the probabilities
are
uh the model parameters sort of in our
bigram language model so far.
Uh but you have to keep in mind that
here we are storing everything in a
table format, the probabilities. But
what's coming up as a brief preview is
that these numbers will not be kept
explicitly but these numbers will be
calculated by a neural network.
So that's coming up.
And we want to change and tune the
parameters of these neural networks. We
want to change these parameters to
maximize the likelihood, the product of
the probabilities.
Now maximizing the likelihood is
equivalent to maximizing the log
likelihood because log is a monotonic
function.
Here's the graph of log.
And basically all it is doing is it's uh
just a scaling your um you can look at
it as just a scaling of the loss
function.
And so the optimization problem here and
here are actually equivalent because
this is just a scaling. You can look at
it that way.
And so these are two identical
optimization problems.
Um
maximizing the log likelihood is
equivalent to minimizing the negative
log likelihood.
And then in practice people actually
minimize the average negative log
likelihood to get numbers like 2.4.
And then this summarizes the quality of
your model.
And we'd like to minimize it and make it
as small as possible.
And the lowest it can get is zero.
And the lower it is
the better off your model is because
it's assigning it's assigning high
probabilities to your data.
Now let's estimate the probability over
the entire training set just to make
sure that we get something around 2.4.
Let's run this over the entire oops.
Let's take out the print statement as
well.
Okay, 2.45 over the entire training set.
Now what I'd like to show you is that
you can actually evaluate the
probability for any word that you want.
Like for example
if we just test a single word Andre and
bring back the print statement
then you see that Andre is actually kind
of like an unlikely word. Like on
average
um we take three log probability to
represent it. And roughly that's because
EJ apparently is very uncommon as an
example.
Now
think through this um
when I take Andre and I append Q and I
test the probability of it Andre Q
we actually get um infinity.
And that's because JQ has a 0%
probability according to our model. So
the log likelihood
so the log of zero will be negative
infinity. We get infinite loss.
So this is kind of undesirable, right?
Because we plugged in a string that
could be like a somewhat reasonable
name. But basically what this is saying
is that this model is exactly 0% likely
to uh to predict this name
and our loss is infinity on this
example.
And really what the reason for that is
that J
is followed by Q
uh zero times. Uh where is Q? JQ is zero
and so JQ is 0% likely.
So it's actually kind of gross and
people don't like this too much. To fix
this, there's a very simple fix that
people like to do to sort of like smooth
out your model a little bit that is
called model smoothing.
And roughly what's happening is that we
will we will add some fake counts.
So imagine adding a count of one to
everything.
So we add a count of one
like this
and then we recalculate the
probabilities.
And that's model smoothing and you can
add as much as you like. You can add
five and that will give you a smoother
model.
And the more you add here
the more uniform model you're going to
have. And the less you add,
um the more more peaked model you're
going to have, of course.
So one is like a pretty decent count to
add and that will ensure that there will
be no zeros in our probability matrix P.
And so this will of course change the
generations a little bit. In this case
it didn't but it in principle it could.
But what that's going to do now is that
nothing will be infinity unlikely.
So now
our model will predict some other
probability and we see that JQ now has a
very small probability. So the model
still finds it very surprising that this
was a word or bigram but we don't get
negative infinity.
So it's kind of like a nice fix that
people like to apply sometimes and it's
called model smoothing. Okay, so we've
now trained a respectable bigram
character level language model and we
saw that we both
a sort of trained the model by looking
at the counts of all the bigrams and
normalizing the rows to get probability
distributions.
We saw that we can also then use those
parameters of this model to perform
sampling of new words.
So, we sample new names according to
those distributions. And we also saw
that we can evaluate the quality of this
model.
And the quality of this model is
summarized in a single number, which is
the negative log likelihood. And the
lower this number is, the better the
model is
because it is giving high probabilities
to the actual next characters in all the
bigrams in our training set.
So, that's all well and good. But we've
arrived at this model explicitly by
doing something that felt sensible. We
were just performing counts, and then we
were normalizing those counts.
Now, what I would like to do is I would
like to take an alternative approach. We
will end up in a very, very similar
position, but the approach will look
very different because I would like to
cast the problem of bigram character
level language modeling into the neural
network framework.
And in the neural network framework,
we're going to approach things slightly
differently, but again, end up in a very
similar spot. I'll go into that later.
Now, our neural network is going to be a
still a bigram character level language
model. So, it receives a single
character as an input.
Then there's neural network with some
weights or some parameters W.
And it's going to output the probability
distribution over the next character in
a sequence. It's going to make guesses
as to what is likely to follow this
character that was input to the model.
And then in addition to that, we're
going to be able to evaluate any setting
of the parameters of the neural net
because we have the loss function.
The negative log likelihood. So, we're
going to take a look at these
probability distributions, and we're
going to use the labels
which are basically just the identity of
the next character in that bigram, the
second character.
So, knowing what second character
actually comes next in the bigram allows
us to then look at what how high of a
probability the model assigns to that
character.
And then we of course want the
probability to be very high.
And that is another way of saying that
the loss is low.
So, we're going to use gradient-based
optimization then to tune the parameters
of this network because we have the loss
function and we're going to minimize it.
So, we're going to tune the weights so
that the neural net is correctly
predicting the probabilities for the
next character.
So, let's get started. The first thing I
want to do is I want to compile the
training set of this neural network,
right? So, create
the training set
of all the bigrams.
Okay?
And
here
I'm going to copy-paste this code
because this code iterates over all the
bigrams.
So, here we start with the words. We
iterate over all the bigrams. And
previously, as you recall, we did the
counts. But now we're not going to do
counts. We're just creating a training
set.
Now, this training set will be made up
of two lists.
We have the
inputs
and the targets, the the labels.
And these bigrams will denote XY. Those
are the characters, right?
And so, we're given the first character
of the bigram and then we're trying to
predict the next one.
Both of these are going to be integers.
So, here we'll take X's. data.append is
just
X1. Y's.data.append IX2.
And then here
we actually don't want lists of
integers. We will create uh tensors out
of these. So, X's is torch.tensor
X's and Y's is torch.tensor of Y's.
And then we don't actually want to take
all the words just yet because I want
everything to be manageable. Uh so,
let's just do the first word, which is
Emma.
And then it's clear what these X's and
Y's would be.
Here, let me print
character one, character two, just so
you see what's going on here.
So, the bigrams of these characters is
.e, em, mm, ma, a. So, so this single
word, as I mentioned, has 1 2 3 4 5
examples for our neural network.
There are five separate examples in
Emma.
And those examples are summarized here.
When the input to the neural neural
network is integer zero,
the desired label is integer five, which
corresponds to e.
When the input to the neural network is
five, we want its weights to be arranged
so that 13 gets a very high probability.
When 13 is put in, we want 13 to have a
high probability.
When 13 is put in, we also want one to
have a high probability.
When one is input, we want zero to have
a very high probability. So, there are
five separate input examples to a neural
net
in this data set.
I wanted to add a tangent of a note of
caution to be careful with a lot of the
APIs of some of these frameworks.
You saw me silently use torch.Tensor
with a lowercase t, and the output
looked right.
But, you should be aware that there's
actually two ways of constructing a
tensor. There's a torch.lowercase
tensor, and there's also a torch.capital
tensor class, which you can also
construct. Uh so, you can actually call
both. You can also do torch.capital
tensor,
and you get an x's and y's as well.
So, that's not confusing at all.
Um
There are threads on what is the
difference between these two.
And um
unfortunately, the docs are just like
not clear on the difference. And when
you look at the the docs of lowercase
tensor, constructs tensor with no
autograd history by copying data.
It's just like it doesn't
it doesn't make sense. So, the actual
difference, as far as I can tell, is
explained eventually in this random
thread that you can Google.
And really, it comes down to, I believe,
that um
where is this?
torch.Tensor infers the dtype, the data
type, automatically, while torch.Tensor
just returns a float tensor.
I would recommend stick to torch.lower
case tensor.
So, um
indeed, we see that when I construct
this with a capital T, the data type
here of X's is float 32.
But, torch.lower case tensor
you see how it's now X.dtype is now
integer.
So, um
it's advised that you use lower case T
and you can read more about it if you
like in some of these threads.
Uh but basically
um
I'm pointing out some of these things
beca- because I want to caution you and
I want you to re- get used to reading a
lot of documentation and reading through
a lot of uh Q&A's and threads like this.
And um
you know, some of this stuff is
unfortunately not easy and not very well
documented and you have to be careful
out there. What we want here is integers
because that's what makes uh sense. Um
and so uh lower case tensor is what we
are using. Okay, now we want to think
through how we're going to feed in these
examples into a neural network.
Now, it's not quite as straightforward
as n-
plugging it in because these examples
right now are integers. So, there's like
a 0, 5, or 13. It gives us the index of
the character and you can't just plug an
integer index into a neural net.
These neural nets uh right are sort of
made up of these neurons.
And uh these neurons have weights. And
as you saw in micrograd, these weights
act multiplicatively on the inputs. WX
plus B, there's tanh's and so on. And
so, it doesn't really make sense to make
an input neuron take on integer values
that you feed in and then multiply on
with weights.
So, instead, a common way of encoding
integers is what's called one-hot
encoding.
In one-hot encoding, uh we take an
integer like 13 and we create a vector
that is all zeros except for the 13th
dimension, which we turn to a one.
And then that vector can feed into a
neural net.
Now, conveniently,
uh PyTorch actually has something called
the one-hot uh uh
um
function inside torch.nn.functional.
It takes a tensor made up of integers.
Um
long is a is a is an integer.
and it also takes a number of classes,
um
which is how large you want your uh
tensor uh your vector to be.
So here, let's import is a common way of
importing it.
And then let's do F.one_hot.
And we feed in uh the integers that we
want to encode.
So we can actually feed in the entire
array of X's.
And we can tell it that num_classes is
27.
So it doesn't have to try to guess it.
It may have guessed that it's only 13
and would give us an incorrect result.
So this is the one-hot. Let's call this
X_enc for X encoded.
And then we see that X_encoded.shape is
5 by 27.
And uh
we can also visualize it, plt.imshow of
X_enc,
to make it a little bit more clear
because this is a little messy.
So we see that we've encoded all the
five examples uh into vectors.
We have five examples, so we have five
rows, and each row here is now an
example into a neural net.
And we see that the appropriate bit is
turned on as a one, and everything else
is zero.
So um
here for example, the the zeroth bit is
turned on, the fifth bit is turned on,
13th bits are turned on for both of
these examples, and then the first bit
here is turned on.
So that's how we can encode um integers
into vectors.
And then these vectors can feed in to
neural nets. One more issue to be
careful with here, by the way, is
let's look at the data type of X
encoding. We always want to be careful
with data types.
What would you expect X encoding's data
type to be? When we're plugging numbers
into neural nets, we don't want them to
be integers. We want them to be floating
point numbers that can take on various
values. But the D type here is actually
64-bit integer.
And the reason for that, I suspect, is
that one hot received a 64-bit integer
here and it returned to the same data
type.
And when you look at the signature of
one hot, it doesn't even take a D type,
a desired data type of the output
tensor.
And so we can't In a lot of functions in
torch, we'd be able to do something like
D type equals torch.float32,
which is what we want, but one hot does
not support that.
So instead, we're going to want to cast
this to float like this.
So that these
everything is the same.
Everything looks the same, but the D
type is float 32. And floats can feed
into um neural nets. So now let's
construct our first neuron.
This neuron will look at these input
vectors.
And as you remember from micrograd,
these neurons basically perform a very
simple function, wx plus b, where wx is
a dot product, right?
So we can achieve the same thing here.
Let's first define the weights of this
neuron. Basically, where are the initial
weights at initialization for this
neuron?
Let's initialize them with torch.randn.
torch.randn
is um
fills a tensor with random numbers
drawn from a normal distribution.
And a normal distribution has a
probability uh density function like
this. And so most of the numbers drawn
from this distribution will be around
zero,
uh but some of them will be as high as
almost three and so on. And very few
numbers will be above three in
magnitude.
So we need to take a size as an input
here.
And I'm going to use size as 27 by 1.
So, 27 by 1, and then let's visualize W.
So, W is a column vector of 27 numbers.
And uh these weights are then multiplied
by the inputs.
So, now to perform this multiplication,
we can take X encoding
and we can multiply it with W.
This is a matrix multiplication operator
in PyTorch.
And the output of this operation is 5 by
1.
The reason it's 5 by 1 is the following.
We took X encoding, which is 5 by 27,
and we multiplied it by 27 by 1.
And
in matrix multiplication,
you see that the output will become 5 by
1 because these 27 will multiply and
add.
So, basically what we're seeing here,
out out of this operation,
is we are seeing the five um
activations
of this neuron
on these five inputs. And we've
evaluated all of them in parallel. We
didn't feed in just a single input to
this single neuron. We fed in
simultaneously all the five inputs into
the same neuron,
and in parallel, PyTorch has evaluated
the WX plus B, but here it's just WX.
There's no bias.
It has valued W W times X for all of
them uh independently. Now, instead of a
single neuron though, I would like to
have 27 neurons, and I'll show you in a
second why I want 27 neurons.
So, instead of having just a one here,
which is indicating this presence of one
single neuron,
we can use 27.
And then when W is 27 by 27,
this will in parallel evaluate all the
27 neurons on all the five inputs.
Giving us a much better, much much
bigger result.
So, now what we've done is 5 by 27
multiplied 27 by 27.
And the output of this is now 5 by 27.
So, we can see that the shape of this
is 5 by 27.
So, what is every element here telling
us, right?
It's telling us for every one of 27
neurons that we created,
what is the firing rate of those neurons
on every one of those five examples?
So,
the element, for example, 3  13
is giving us the firing rate of the 13th
neuron looking at the third input.
And the way this was achieved is by a
dot product
between the third input
and the 13th column
of this W matrix here.
Okay? So, using matrix multiplication,
we can very efficiently evaluate
the dot product between lots of input
examples in a batch.
And lots of neurons, where all of those
neurons have weights in the columns of
those Ws.
And in matrix multiplication, we're just
doing those dot products and
in parallel. Just to show you that this
is the case, we can take X and we can
take the third
row.
And we can take the W and take its 13th
column.
And then we can do X and get three.
Element-wise multiply with W at 13.
And sum that up. That's WX plus B.
Uh well, there's no plus B. It's just WX
dot product. And that's
this number.
So, you see that this is just being done
efficiently by the matrix multiplication
operation for all the input examples and
for all the output neurons of this first
layer.
Okay, so we fed our 27-dimensional
inputs into a first layer of a neural
net that has 27 neurons, right? So, we
have 27 inputs and now we have 27
neurons. These neurons perform W * X.
They don't have a bias and they don't
have a non-linearity like tanh. We're
going to leave them to be a linear
layer.
In addition to that, we're not going to
have any other layers. This is going to
be it. It's just going to be
the dumbest, smallest, simplest neural
net, which is just a single linear
layer.
And now I'd like to explain what I want
those 27 outputs to be.
Intuitively, what we're trying to
produce here for every single input
example is we're trying to produce some
kind of a probability distribution for
the next character in a sequence. And
there's 27 of them.
But we have to come up with like precise
semantics for exactly how we're going to
interpret these 27 numbers that these
neurons take on.
Now, intuitively,
you see here that these numbers are
negative and some of them are positive,
etc.
And that's because these are coming out
of a neural net layer initialized with
these um
uh normal distribution
uh parameters.
But what we want is we want something
like we had here. Like each row here
told us the counts and then we
normalized the counts to get
probabilities. And we want something
similar to come out of a neural net.
But what we just have right now is just
some negative and positive numbers.
Now, we want those numbers to somehow
represent the probabilities for the next
character.
But you see that probabilities, they
they have a special structure. They um
they're positive numbers and they sum to
one.
And so, that doesn't just come out of a
neural net.
And then, they can't be counts because
uh these counts are positive and counts
are integers.
So, counts are also not really a good
thing to output from a neural net.
So, instead what the neural net is going
to output and how we are going to
interpret the
the 27 numbers is that these 27 numbers
are giving us log counts
basically.
Um so, instead of giving us counts
directly like in this table, they're
giving us log counts.
And to get the counts, we're going to
take the log counts and we're going to
exponentiate them.
Now,
exponentiation
takes the following form.
Um it takes numbers
that are negative or they are positive.
It takes the entire real line. And then
if you plug in negative numbers, you're
going to get e to the x, which is
uh always below one.
So, you're getting numbers lower than
one.
And if you plug in numbers greater than
zero, you're getting numbers greater
than one
all the way growing to the infinity.
And this here grows to zero.
So, basically we're going to take these
numbers
here.
And
instead of them being positive and
negative in all of the place, we're
going to interpret them as log counts
and then we're going to element-wise
exponentiate these numbers.
Exponentiating them now gives us
something like this.
And you see that these numbers now
because of they went through an
exponent, all the negative numbers
turned into numbers below one like
0.338.
And all the positive numbers originally
turned into even more positive numbers
sort of greater than one.
Um so, like for example, seven
um is some positive number over here. Um
that is greater than zero.
But, exponentiated outputs here
um basically give us something that we
can use and interpret as the equivalent
of counts or originally. So, you see
these counts here, 1 12 7 51 1 etc.
The neural net is kind of now predicting
uh
counts.
And these counts are positive numbers.
They can never be below zero, so that
makes sense. And uh they can now take on
various values
depending on the settings of W.
So, let me break this down.
We're going to interpret these to be the
log counts.
Another word for this that is often used
is so-called logits.
These are logits, log counts.
And these will be sort of the counts.
Logits exponentiated.
And this is equivalent to the N matrix,
sort of, the N
array that we used previously. Remember,
this was the N.
This is the the array of counts. And
each row here are the counts for the
for the um
next character, sort of.
So, those are the counts. And now the
probabilities are just the counts um
normalized.
And so, um
I'm not going to find the same, but
basically, I'm not going to scroll all
over the place.
We've already done this. We want to
counts that sum along the first
dimension, and we want to keep dims as
true.
We went over this, and this is how we
normalize the rows of our counts matrix
to get our probabilities.
probs
So, now these are the probabilities.
And these are the counts that we have
currently. And now when I show the
probabilities,
you see that um
every row here,
of course,
will sum to one
because they're normalized.
And the shape of this
is 5 by 27.
And so really what we've achieved is for
every one of our five examples, we now
have a row that came out of a neural
net.
And because of the transformations here,
we made sure that this output of this
neural net now are probabilities or we
can interpret to be probabilities.
So,
our WX here gave us logits
and then we interpret those to be log
counts.
We exponentiate to get something that
looks like counts.
And then we normalize those counts to
get a probability distribution.
And all of these are differentiable
operations.
So, what we've done now is we are taking
inputs.
We have differentiable operations that
we can back propagate through
and we're getting out probability
distributions.
So, um for example, for the zeroth
example that fed in,
right, which was um
the zeroth example here was a one-hot
vector of zero.
And um
it basically corresponded to feeding in
uh
this example here. So, we're feeding in
a dot into a neural net. And the way we
fed the dot into a neural net is that we
first got its index.
Then we one-hot encoded it.
Then it went into the neural net and out
came
this distribution of probabilities.
And its shape
is 27. There's 27 numbers and we're
going to interpret this as the neural
net's assignment for how likely
every one of these characters um
the 27 characters are to come next.
And as we tune the weights W,
we're going to be of course getting
different probabilities out for any
character that you input.
And so now the question is just can we
optimize and find a good W
such that the probabilities coming out
are pretty good. And the way we measure
pretty good is by the loss function.
Okay, so I organized everything into a
single summary so that hopefully it's a
bit more clear. So it starts here.
We have an input data set.
We have some inputs to the neural net
and we have some labels for the correct
next character in a sequence. And these
are integers.
Here I'm using uh torch generators now
so that you see the same numbers that I
see.
And I'm generating
um
27 neurons weights
and each neuron here receives 27 inputs.
Then here we're going to plug in all the
input examples x's into a neural net. So
here, this is a forward pass.
First, we have to encode all of the
inputs into one-hot representations.
So we have 27 classes, we pass in these
integers and x inc becomes a array that
is 5 by 27.
Zeros except for a few ones.
We then multiply this in the first layer
of a neural net to get logits.
Exponentiate the logits to get fake
counts, sort of.
And normalize these counts to get
probabilities.
So the la- these last two lines by the
way here are called the softmax.
Uh which I pulled up here.
Softmax is a very often used layer in a
neural net that takes these z's which
are logits,
exponentiates them,
and uh divides and normalizes. It's a
way of taking outputs of a neural net
layer and these uh these outputs can be
positive or negative.
And it outputs probability
distributions. It outputs something that
is always sums to one and are positive
numbers, just like probabilities.
Um so it's kind of like a normalization
function if you want to think of it that
way. And you can put it on top of any
other linear layer inside a neural net
and it basically makes a neural net
output probabilities. That's very often
used and we used it as well here.
So this is the forward pass and that's
how we made a neural net output
probability.
Now
you'll notice that
um
all of these
this entire forward pass is made up of
differentiable
layers. Everything here we can back
propagate through. And we saw some of
the back propagation in micrograd.
This is just
multiplication and addition. All that's
happening here is just multiply and then
add. And we know how to back propagate
through them.
Exponentiation we know how to back
propagate through.
And then here we are summing and sum is
is easily back propagatable as well.
And division as well. So everything here
is differentiable operation
and we can back propagate through.
Now we achieve these probabilities which
are 5 by 27.
For every single example we have a
vector of probabilities that sum to one.
And then here I wrote a bunch of stuff
uh to sort of like break down uh the
examples.
So we have five examples making up Emma,
right?
And there are five bigrams inside Emma.
So bigram example a bigram example one
is that E is the beginning character
right after dot.
And the indexes for these are zero and
five.
So then we feed in a zero.
That's the input to the neural net.
We get probabilities from the neural net
that are 27 numbers.
And then the label is five because E
actually comes after dot.
So that's the label.
And then
we use this label five to index into the
probability distribution here.
So this index five here is 0 1 2 3 4 5.
It's this number here.
Which is here.
So that's basically the probability
assigned by the neural net to the actual
correct character.
You see that the network currently
thinks that this next character that E
following dot is only 1% likely. Which
is of course not very good, right?
Because this actually is a training
example and the network thinks that this
is currently very very unlikely. But
that's just because we didn't get very
lucky in generating a good setting of W.
So right now this network thinks this is
unlikely and 0.01 is not a good outcome.
So the log likelihood then
is very negative.
And the negative log likelihood is very
positive.
And so four is a very high negative log
likelihood and that means we're going to
have a high loss.
Because what is the loss? The loss is
just the average negative log
likelihood.
So the second character is E M.
And you see here that also the network
thought that M following E is very
unlikely, 1%.
Uh the for M following M it thought it
was 2%.
And for A following M it actually
thought it was 7% likely. So just by
chance this one actually has a pretty
good probability and therefore a pretty
low negative log likelihood.
And finally here it thought this was 1%
likely.
So overall our average negative log
likelihood, which is the loss, the total
loss that summarizes basically the how
well this network currently works at
least on this one word, not on the full
data set, just the one word, is 3.76.
Which is actually very fairly high loss.
This is not a very good setting of Ws.
Now here's what we can do.
We're currently getting 3.76.
We can actually come here and we can
change our W. We can resample it. So let
me just add one to have a different
seed.
And then we get a different W.
And then we can rerun this.
And with this different seed with this
different setting of Ws we now get 3.37.
So this is a much better W, right? And
that and it's better because the
probability just happened to come out
higher for the for the characters that
actually are next.
And so you can imagine actually just
resampling this, you know, we can try
two.
So
Okay, this was not very good.
Let's try one more.
We can try three.
Okay, this was terrible setting because
we have a very high loss.
So
anyway, I'm going to erase this.
What what I'm doing here, which is just
guess and check of randomly assigning
parameters and seeing if the network is
good, that is amateur hour. That's not
how you optimize a neural net. The way
you optimize a neural net is you start
with some random guess, and we're going
to commit to this one even though it's
not very good.
But now the big deal is we have a loss
function.
So this loss
is made up only of differentiable
operations.
And we can minimize the loss by tuning
W's by computing the gradients of the
loss with respect to these W matrices.
And so then we can tune W to minimize
the loss and find a good setting of W
using gradient-based optimization. So
let's see how that will work. Now things
are actually going to look almost
identical to what we had with micrograd.
So here I pulled up the lecture from
micrograd, the notebook. It's from this
repository.
And when I scroll all the way to the end
where we left off with micrograd, we had
something very very similar.
We had a number of input examples. In
this case, we had four input examples
inside X's.
And we had their targets. These are
targets.
Just like here, we have our X's now, but
we have five of them, and they're now
integers instead of vectors.
But we're going to convert our integers
to vectors, except our vectors will be
27 large instead of three large.
And then here what we did is first we
did a forward pass where where ran a
neural net on all of the inputs
to get predictions.
Our neural net at the time, this NFX,
was a net a multi-layer perceptron.
Our neural net is going to look
different because our neural net is just
a single layer.
Single linear layer followed by a
softmax.
So, that's our neural net.
And the loss here was the mean squared
error. So, we simply subtracted the
prediction from the ground truth and
squared it and summed it all up. And
that was the loss. And loss was the
single number that summarized the
quality of the neural net. And when loss
is low, like almost zero, that means the
neural net is um
predicting correctly.
So, we had a single number that uh that
summarized the
uh the performance of the neural net.
And everything here was differentiable
and was stored in massive compute graph.
And then we iterated over all the
parameters. We made sure that the
gradients are set to zero.
And we called loss.backward.
And loss.backward initiated
backpropagation at the final output node
of loss. Right? So,
yeah, remember these expressions? We had
loss all the way at the end. We start
backpropagation and we went all the way
back.
And we made sure that we populated all
the parameters.grad.
So, that grad started at zero, but
backpropagation filled it in.
And then in the update, we iterated over
all the parameters and we simply did a
parameter update where every single uh
element of our parameters was nudged in
the opposite direction of the gradient.
And so, we're going to do the exact same
thing here.
Uh so, I'm going to pull this up
on the side here
so that we have it available. And we're
actually going to do the exact same
thing.
So, this was the forward pass. So, where
we did this.
And probs is our Ypred.
So, now we have to evaluate the loss,
but we're not using the mean squared
error. we're using the negative log
likelihood because we are doing
classification, we're not doing
regression, as it's called.
So, here we want to calculate loss.
Now, the way we calculate it is is just
this average negative log likelihood.
Now, this probs here
has a shape of 5 by 27.
And so, to get all the we basically want
to pluck out the probabilities at the
correct indices here.
So, in particular, because the labels
are stored here in the array wise,
basically what we're after is for the
first example, we're looking at
probability of five, right? At index
five.
For the second example,
at the the second row or row index one,
we are interested in the probability
assigned to index 13.
At the second example, we also have 13.
At the third row, we want one.
And at the last row, which is four, we
want zero. So, these are the
probabilities we're interested in,
right?
And you can see that they're not amazing
as we saw above.
So, these are the probabilities we want,
but we want like a more efficient way to
access these probabilities. Uh not just
listing them out in a tuple like this.
So, it turns out that the way to do this
in PyTorch, uh one of the ways at least,
is we can basically pass in all of these
Sorry about that. All of these um
integers in a vectors.
So, the
these ones, you see how they're just 0 1
2 3 4,
we can actually create that using MP not
MP, sorry, torch.arange of five.
0 1 2 3 4.
So, we can index here with torch.arange
of five.
And here, we index with wise.
And you see that that gives us
exactly these numbers.
So, that plugs out the probabilities of
that the neural network assigns to the
correct next character.
Now, we take those probabilities and we
don't we actually look at the log
probability. So, we want to dot log.
And then, we want to just average that
up. So, take the mean of all of that.
And then, it's the negative average log
likelihood that is the loss.
So, the loss here is
3.7 something. And you see that this
loss, 3.76, 3.76 is exactly as we've
obtained before, but this is a
vectorized form of that expression.
So, we get the same loss.
And this same loss we can consider sort
of as part of this forward pass.
And we've achieved here now loss.
Okay, so we made our way all the way to
loss. We defined the forward pass. We
forwarded the network and the loss. Now,
we're ready to do backward pass.
So, backward pass.
We want to first make sure that all the
gradients are reset. So, they're at
zero.
Now, in PyTorch, you can set the
gradients to be zero, but you can also
just set it to none. And setting it to
none is more efficient. And PyTorch will
interpret none as like a lack of a
gradient and is the same as zeros.
So, this is a way to set to zero the
gradient.
And now, we do loss.backward.
Before we do loss.backward, we need one
more thing. If you remember from
micrograd,
PyTorch actually requires
that we pass in requires_grad is true.
Uh so that we tell
PyTorch that we are interested in
calculating gradients for this leaf
tensor. By default, this is false.
So, let me recalculate with that.
And then, set to none and loss.backward.
Now, something magical happened when
loss of backward was run.
Because PyTorch, just like micrograd,
when we did the forward pass here,
it keeps track of all the operations
under the hood. It builds a full
computational graph.
Just like the graphs we could produce in
micrograd, those graphs exist inside
PyTorch.
And so, it knows all the dependencies
and all the mathematical operations of
everything.
And when you then calculate the loss, we
can call a dot backward on it.
And dot backward then fills in the
gradients of all the intermediates all
the way back to W's, which are the
parameters of our neural net. So, now we
can do W.grad,
and we see that it has structure.
There's stuff inside it.
And these gradients, every single
element here,
so W.shape is 27 by 27.
W.grad's shape is the same, 27 by 27.
And every element of W.grad
is telling us
the influence of that weight on the loss
function.
So, for example, this number all the way
here,
if this element, the 0 0 element of W,
because the gradient is positive, it's
telling us that this has a positive
influence on the loss, slightly nudging
W
slightly taking W00
and adding a small H to it
would increase the loss mildly because
this gradient is positive.
Some of these gradients are also
negative.
So, that's telling us about the gradient
information, and we can use this
gradient information to update the
weights of this neural network. So,
let's now do the update. It's going to
be very similar to what we had in
micrograd. We need no uh loop over all
the parameters because we only have one
parameter uh tensor, and that is W. So,
we simply do W.data plus equals uh, the
We can actually copy this almost
exactly. -0.1 *
uh, W.grad.
Um,
and that would be the update to the
tensor.
So, that updates the tensor.
And because the tensor is updated, we
would expect that now the loss should
decrease.
So, here, if I print loss
.item,
it was 3.76, right? So, we've updated
the W here. So, if I recalculate forward
pass,
loss now should be slightly lower. So,
3.76 goes to
3.74.
And then, we can again set to set grad
to none and backward update.
And now the parameters changed again.
So, if we recalculate the forward pass,
we expect a lower loss again, 3.72.
Okay, and this is again doing the We're
now doing gradient descent.
And when we achieve a low loss, that
will mean that the network is assigning
high probabilities to the correct next
characters. Okay, so I rearranged
everything and I put it all together
from scratch.
So, here is where we construct our data
set of bigrams.
You see that we are still iterating only
on the first word, Emma.
I'm going to change that in a second. I
added a number that counts the number of
elements in X's, so that we explicitly
see the number of examples is five.
Because currently we're just working
with Emma, and there's five bigrams
there.
And here I added a loop of exactly what
we had before. So, we had 10 iterations
of gradient descent, of forward pass,
backward pass, and an update. And so,
running these two cells, initialization
and gradient descent
gives us some improvement on uh the loss
function.
But now, I want to use all the words.
And there's not five, but 228,000
bigrams now.
However, this should require no
modification whatsoever. Everything
should just run because all the code we
wrote doesn't care if there's five
bigrams or 228,000 bigrams. And with
everything, we should just work. So,
you see that this will just run.
But now we are optimizing over the
entire training set of all the bigrams.
And you see now that we are decreasing
very slightly. So, actually, we can
probably afford a larger learning rate.
We can probably afford even larger
learning rate.
Even 50 seems to work on this very, very
simple example, right? So, let me
re-initialize, and let's run 100
iterations.
See what happens.
Okay.
We seem to be
coming up to some pretty good losses
here. 2.47.
Let me run 100 more.
What is the number that we expect, by
the way, in the loss? We expect to get
something around what we had originally,
actually.
So, all the way back, if you remember,
in the beginning of this video, when we
optimized uh just by counting,
our loss was roughly 2.47
after we added smoothing.
But before smoothing, we had roughly
2.45
uh likelihood.
Um sorry, loss.
And so, that's actually roughly the
vicinity of what we expect to achieve.
But before we achieved it by counting,
and here we are achieving the roughly
the same result, but with gradient-based
optimization.
So, we come to about 2.4
6, 2.45, etc.
And that makes sense because
fundamentally, we're not taking any
additional information. We're still just
taking in the previous character and
trying to predict the next one. But
instead of doing it explicitly by
counting and normalizing,
we are doing it with gradient-based
learning. And it just so happens that
the explicit approach happens to very
well optimize the loss function without
any need for gradient-based optimization
because the setup for bigram language
models are is is so straightforward and
so simple. We can just afford to
estimate those probabilities directly
and maintain them in a table.
But the gradient-based approach is
significantly more flexible.
So we've actually gained a lot because
what we can do now is um
we can expand this approach and
complexify the neural net.
So currently we're just taking a single
character and feeding into a neural net
and the neural net is extremely simple.
But we're about to iterate on this
substantially. We're going to be taking
multiple previous characters and we're
going to be feed them in feeding them
into increasingly more complex neural
nets. But fundamentally uh the output of
the neural net will always just be
logits.
And those logits will go through the
exact same transformation. We are going
to take them through a softmax,
calculate the loss function and the
negative log likelihood,
and do gradient-based optimization.
And so actually as we complexify the
neural nets and work all the way up to
transformers,
none of this will really fundamentally
change. None of this will fundamentally
change. The only thing that will change
is
the way we do the forward pass where we
take in some previous characters and
calculate the logits for the next
character in a sequence. That will
become more complex
and uh but we'll use the same machinery
to optimize it.
And um
it's not obvious how we would have
extended this bigram approach into the
case where there are many more
characters at the input because
eventually these tables would get way
too large because there's way too many
combinations of what previous characters
uh could be.
If you only have one previous character,
we can just keep everything in a table,
the counts. But if you have the last 10
characters that are input, we can't
actually keep everything in a table
anymore. So this is fundamentally an
unscalable approach, and the neural
network approach is significantly more
scalable, and it's something that
actually we can improve on over time. So
that's where we will be digging next. I
wanted to point out two more things.
Number one,
I want you to notice that this
X inc here,
this is made up of one-hot vectors, and
then those one-hot vectors are
multiplied by this W matrix.
And we think of this as uh multiple
neurons being forwarded in a fully
connected manner.
But actually what's happening here is
that, for example,
if you have a one-hot vector here that
has a one at, say, the fifth dimension,
then because of the way the matrix
multiplication works,
multiplying that one-hot vector with W
actually ends up plucking out the fifth
row of W.
Logits would become just a fifth row of
W.
And that's because of the way the matrix
multiplication works.
Um
so that's actually what ends up
happening.
So but that's actually exactly what
happened before.
Because remember all the way up here,
we have a bigram. We took the first
character, and then that first character
indexed into a row of this array here.
And that row gave us the probability
distribution for the next character.
So the first character was used as a
lookup into a
uh
matrix here to get the probability
distribution.
Well, that's actually exactly what's
happening here.
Because we're taking the index, we're
encoding it as one-hot, and multiplying
it by W.
So logits literally becomes the
uh the
the appropriate row of W.
And that gets just as before
exponentiated to create the counts
and then normalized and becomes
probability.
So this W here
is literally
the same as this array here.
But W, remember, is the log counts, not
the counts. So it's more precise to say
that W exponentiated
W.exp is this array.
But this array was filled in by counting
and by basically
populating the counts of bigrams,
whereas in the gradient-based framework,
we initialize it randomly and then we
let the loss guide us
to arrive at the exact same array.
So this array exactly here
is
basically the array W at the end of
optimization, except we arrived at it
piece by piece by following the loss.
And that's why we also obtain the same
loss function at the end. And the second
note is if I come here,
remember the smoothing where we added
fake counts to our counts in order to
smooth out and make more uniform the
distributions of these probabilities.
And that prevented us from assigning
zero probability to
um
to any one bigram.
Now, if I increase the count here,
what's happening to the probability?
As I increase the count, probability
becomes more and more uniform.
Right? Because these counts go only up
to like 900 or whatever. So if I'm
adding plus a million to every single
number here, you can see how uh the row
and its probability then when we divide
is just going to become more and more
close to exactly even probability,
uniform distribution.
It turns out that the gradient-based
framework has an equivalent to
smoothing.
In particular,
think through these W's here,
which we initialized randomly.
We could also think about initializing
W's to be zero.
If all the entries of W are zero,
then you'll see that logits will become
all zero.
And then exponentiating those logits
becomes all one.
And then the probabilities turn out to
be exactly uniform.
So, basically when W's are all equal to
each other, or say especially zero,
then the probabilities come out
completely uniform.
So,
trying to incentivize W to be near zero
is basically equivalent to label
smoothing. And the more you incentivize
that in the loss function, the more
smooth distribution you're going to
achieve.
So, this brings us to something that's
called regularization,
where we can actually augment the loss
function to have a small component that
we call a regularization loss.
In particular, what we're going to do is
we can take W,
and we can for example square all of its
entries,
and then we can uh oops.
Sorry about that.
We can take all the entries of W, and we
can sum them.
And because we're squaring, uh there
will be no signs anymore. Um
negatives and positives all get squashed
to be positive numbers.
And then the way this works is you
achieve zero loss if W is exactly or
zero.
But if W has non-zero numbers, you
accumulate loss.
And so, we can actually take this, and
we can add it on here.
So, we can do something like loss plus
W squared
dot sum.
Or let's actually, instead of sum, let's
take a mean, cuz otherwise the sum gets
too large.
So, mean is like a little bit more
manageable.
And then we have a regularization loss
here, let's say 0.01 times,
or something like that. You can choose
the regularization strength.
And then we can just optimize this.
And now this optimization actually has
two components. Not only is it trying to
make all the probabilities work out, but
in addition to that, there's an
additional component that simultaneously
tries to make all W's be zero. Because
if W's are non-zero, you feel a loss.
And so minimizing this, the only way to
do achieve that is for W to be zero.
And so you can think of this as adding
like a spring force or like a gravity
force that that pushes W to be zero.
So W wants to be zero, and the
probabilities want to be uniform, but
they also simultaneously want to match
up your your probabilities as indicated
by the data.
And so the strength of this
regularization is exactly controlling
the amount of counts
that you add here.
Adding a lot more counts here
corresponds to
increasing this number.
Because the more you increase it, the
more this part of the loss function
dominates this part, and the more these
these weights will be unable to grow
because as they grow,
they accumulate way too much loss.
And so if this is strong enough,
then we are not able to overcome the
force of this loss, and we will never
and basically everything will be uniform
predictions.
So I thought that's kind of cool.
Okay, and lastly, before we wrap up,
I wanted to show you how you would
sample from this neural net model.
And I copy-pasted the sampling code from
before.
Where remember that we sampled five
times.
And all we did is we started zero, we
grabbed the current IX row of P.
And that was our probability row
from which we sampled the next index and
just accumulated that and break when
zero.
And running this gave us these results.
I still have the
P in memory, so this is fine.
Now,
this P doesn't come from the row of P.
Instead, it comes from this neural net.
First, we take IX
and we encode it into a one-hot row of X
inc.
This X inc multiplies our W,
which really just plucks out the row of
W corresponding to IX. Really, that's
what's happening.
And that gets our logits, and then we
normalize those logits, exponentiate to
get counts, and then normalize to get uh
the distribution, and then we can sample
from the distribution.
So, if I run this,
kind of anticlimactic or climatic,
depending how you look at it, but we get
the exact same result.
Um
and that's because this is in the
identical model. Not only does it
achieve the same loss, but um as I
mentioned, these are identical models,
and this W is the log counts of what
we've estimated before. But, we came to
this answer in a very different way and
it's got a very different
interpretation. But, fundamentally, this
is basically the same model and gives
the same samples here. And so,
that's kind of cool. Okay, so we've
actually covered a lot of ground. We
introduced the bigram character-level
language model.
We saw how we can train the model, how
we can sample from the model, and how we
can evaluate the quality of the model
using the negative log likelihood loss.
And then we actually trained the model
in two completely different ways that
actually give the same result and the
same model.
In the first way, we just counted up the
frequency of all the bigrams and
normalized.
In the second way, we used the uh
negative log likelihood loss as a guide
to optimizing the counts matrix
uh or the counts array so that the loss
is minimized in the in a gradient-based
framework. And we saw that both of them
give the same result.
And um
that's it.
Now, the second one of these, the
gradient base framework, is much more
flexible. And right now, our neural
network is super simple. We're taking a
single previous character, and we're
taking it through a single linear layer
to calculate the logits.
This is about to complexify. So, in the
follow-up videos, we're going to be
taking more and more of these
characters,
and we're going to be feeding them into
a neural net.
But, this neural net will still output
the exact same thing. The neural net
will output logits.
And these logits will still be
normalized in the exact same way, and
all the loss and everything else in the
gradient gradient base framework,
everything stays identical.
It's just that this neural net will now
complexify all the way to transformers.
So, that's going to be pretty awesome,
and I'm looking forward to it. For now,
bye.